Guide to the H. Lawrence Freeman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Images, circa 1870-1969
  - Photographs-- Headshot and Publicity
    - M-Z (Mason, Mayner, McClain, Montgomery, Mores, Olden, Patterson, Preer, Price, Rocca, Sissile, Smith, Stewart, Swarz, “Uncle Rube,” Verwayan, Walker, Whipper, Woodby) (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - The Martyr Cast, 1947 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - General, undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Oversize group photos, undated (Anita Bush Stock Company, Negro Choral Society, unidentified) (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Photographs--Negatives, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 44)
  - Photographs--Postcard, circa 1898-1915 (identified sitters: Foster, Moss, Thomas), (2 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Photographs--Snapshots
    - Small format, circa 1910-1919 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Small format, circa 1920-1929 (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Small format, circa 1930-1939 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Small format--general, undated (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Medium format, circa 1920-1929 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Medium format, circa 1930-1939 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - Medium format, circa 1940-1949 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Large format, circa 1920-1929 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Large format, circa 1930-1939 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Large format, circa 1940-1949 (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Large format, circa 1950-1959 (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Large format--general, undated (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - Framed photographs, undated (Box 46)
  - Photographs--Daguerreotypes, undated (11) (Box 47)
  - Paintings and sketches
    - Freeman, Family--Framed paintings--by Elcha, undated (Box 48)
      [Restricted: An advance appointment must be made to view this material because it is oversized and requires special handling.]
    - Freeman, H. Lawrence--painting by Elcha, undated (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Freeman, H. Lawrence--sketch, undated (signature illegible) (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Still life--painting by Alan Price, 1949 (Box 42, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Correspondence, 1900-1980, undated
  Contained in this series are letters to and from the Freemans over their entire adult lives. Much material survives from the 1920s and 1930s relating to production of H. Lawrence’s operas. Other highlights include several letters from Carlotta to Valdo, 1915-1918, when she was touring with a theatrical company, and a letter from H. Lawrence to Edward Hipsher with a wealth of biographical detail to assist Hipsher with his entry on Freeman in his book, American Opera and its Composers, 1933. Please see Appendix A for identified correspondents.
  - 1900-1980, undated, (7 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 1 to 7)
- Series V: Writings of H. Lawrence Freeman, 1921-1940s, undated
  Freeman’s non-musical work, including drafts of his unpublished monograph, The Negro in Classical Music and Opera, a newspaper article on "The Musical Outlook," libretti, several plays, and scenarios for his operas make up this series.
  - Aframerican Opera Foundation--Letter Draft, circa 1940s (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Article Draft--“The Musical Outlook,” undated (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Book Draft, undated (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Libretti, undated (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Plays, 1921, undated (Box 50, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Scenarios, undated (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Scenarios--Fragment, undated (Box 49, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Arts Organizations associated with the Freemans, 1920-1982, undated
  Material relating to several different arts organizations in which the Freeman family participated is gathered in this series. The material is organized in alphabetical order by group name. Materials from the Aframerican Opera Foundation include cards, letterhead, and contracts for this organization, and a roll book of members for an earlier version of this group, the Aframerican Opera Guild, from the early 1940s. The Friends Amusement Guild folder includes tickets, fliers, a membership card, a newsletter from 1933, a list of members, and a poem by Leo Evans about the group. Valdo Freeman served as Administrative Secretary for the Negro Actors’ Guild from the mid-1960s until his death in 1972; during the late 1970s Anita continued her husband’s work as chairwoman of various committees. Most of the material related to the Negro Actors’ Guild is from Anita’s work with the group’s assistance program for members who fell on hard times. It also includes a few newsletters from the period of Valdo’s work with the organization, including one memorializing him shortly after his death, and a certificate of memorial for H. Lawrence Freeman. One clipping from the organization’s newspaper in 1939 is present, but partially deteriorated. Documents from the Negro Grand Opera Company include contracts between the three Freemans and the company, books of stock certificates and records of stock sold, and ephemera including promotional materials about the group, an embossing press, letterhead, and a copperplate block for printing the company’s logo. (For more financial records of this organization, please see Series III: Performance Documentation, Box 12, Folder 6, "Financial Documents," many of which relate to the Negro Grand Opera Company.)
  - Aframerican Opera Foundation
    - Documents and contracts, 1920-1924 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Program Draft, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Friends Amusement Guild--Documents and Ephemera, 1931-1935, undated (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Negro Actors’ Guild--Documents and Clipping, 1939 circa 1954-1982 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Negro Grand Opera Company
    - Documents and contracts, 1920-1923 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - Stock certificate books, 1920 (Box 51, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Company records book, 1920 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Copperplate logo stamp, circa 1920 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Company embossing stamp, circa 1920 (Box 51, Folder 5)
- Series VII: Audio, 1971-1972, undated
  A copy of an interview Valdo Freeman gave to Yale’s Oral History of American Music project in 1971, along with a recording of him playing excerpts of his father’s music, make up this series.
  - Valdo Freeman--Interview--American Music Series, 1971, (reel to reel) (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Valdo Freeman--Interview--American Music Series, 1972, (reel to reel) (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Vendetta--“Clarissa Aria” and “Amita Aria,” undated, (2 LPs) (Box 52, Folder 3)
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1898-1954, undated
  H. Lawrence Freeman or other family members compiled many scrapbooks during his lifetime— six are extant in this series, several of which overlap in dates. The scrapbooks contain clippings, correspondence, programs, and other ephemera related to the Freeman’s careers; some are annotated by H. Lawrence Freeman. This series also includes a file of loose clippings. In addition to articles written by H. Lawrence Freeman or related to his career, he had a collection of clippings—articles and pictures—about African-American performing artists. A few complete issues of periodicals are also included here.
  - Loose scrapbook pages, 1930-1935, (5 Folders) (Box 53, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Loose scrapbook pages--oversize, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Loose clippings and printed materials--general, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 54, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Loose clippings--African-Americans in the arts, undated (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Black scrapbook, 1908-1940 (Box 55)
  - Black scrapbook, 1937 and undated (Box 56)
  - Large scrapbook with missing covers, 1920-1930 (Box 57)
  - Large brown scrapbook--50th anniversary cards, 1949 (Box 58)
  - Small marbled scrapbook, 1898-1929 (Box 59)
  - Wallpaper scrapbook, 1918-1928 (Box 60)
- Series IX: Personal, circa 1898-1972, undated
  This series contains resumes for H. Lawrence Freeman, invitations and programs for non-professional events he attended and for his funeral, personal documents related to other members of the family, and personal ephemera, including a violin that belonged either to H. Lawrence or Valdo Freeman. There is a folder of documentation about the "Military Boy Scouts," a Harlem group to which Valdo Freeman belonged circa 1910-1918, with some photographs. Also included are the program and menu for a dinner in honor of W.E.B. DuBois, 1924, and program of the Fourth Pan-African Congress, 1927.
  - Documents and photographs, circa 1915-1972 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - General, 1933-1938, undated (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera
    - Brass plaque (Box 61)
    - Mirror with photo on back hhh (Box 61)
    - Scissors (Box 61)
    - Straight razor and Box (Box 61)
    - Stamp with numerical wheel (Box 61)
    - Stamps with faces (2) (Box 61)
    - Valdo Freeman’s Violin--German, circa 1898 (Box 62)